<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/rushkoff-archive/feed/articles.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/rushkoff-archive/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-03-09T16:40:19+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/feed/articles.xml</id><title type="html">Rushkoff Archive | Articles</title><subtitle>Douglas Rushkoff&apos;s Article Archive</subtitle><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><entry><title type="html">How Cultivating Awe Can Save the World</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/how-cultivating-awe-can-save-the-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Cultivating Awe Can Save the World" /><published>2023-04-18T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-18T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/how-cultivating-awe-can-save-the-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/how-cultivating-awe-can-save-the-world.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is the last in a series of five pieces about</em> <a href="https://medium.com/@rushkoff/dont-get-people-to-do-anything-9d59a1cf29a0"><em>changing the register</em></a><em>, which just means engendering the attitudes and behaviors we want to see in ourselves by intervening in the cultural landscape instead of manipulating people. The first three interventions were to</em> <a href="https://medium.com/@rushkoff/if-it-aint-real-don-t-fix-it-c080b27f82c5"><em>Denaturalize Power</em></a><em>,</em> <a href="https://medium.com/@rushkoff/everything-is-up-for-discussion-94cb071e2950"><em>Trigger Agency</em></a><em>, and</em> <a href="https://medium.com/p/38f472e75d70/edit"><em>Resocialize People</em></a><em>. I saved the best one for last.</em></p>

<p>Our experiences of collectivity engender a state of awe. This is what people are after when they attend a festival, a rave, a concert, or even a museum or natural wonder. It’s not just a fleeting high that we get, but an experience of the dissolution of self and a sense of connection to everything else.</p>

<p>It’s awesome and real. It’s also pro-social and capable of helping us mobilize to achieve collective <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eudaimonia"><em>eudaimonia</em></a>: an ideal from Aristotelian thought that venerates the liberated condition of universal flourishing.</p>

<p>As scientists are currently learning, an experience of <a href="https://greatergood.berkeley.edu/article/item/eight_reasons_why_awe_makes_your_life_better">awe makes a person more generous</a> while also <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/02/150203133237.htm">regulating cytokines</a> for a more balanced immune response. Cultivating awe means creating opportunities for people to shift from the short-lived pleasure of an online hit (dopamine) to the longer-term social openness of true connection (oxytocin). Awe means experiencing oneself as part of something greater.</p>

<p>To the current, individualist mindset, such connection sounds frightening: it seems like a diminishment of one’s individuality and freedom. Awe, intimacy, and group consciousness seem to compromise <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sovereign_Individual">self-sovereignty</a> and claims to ownership (IP!). In actuality, awe opens us to the fuller realization that our individual and collective identities are mutually reinforcing. Instead of embracing awe, however, the frightened individual panics. We build walls instead of tearing them down.</p>

<p>I discussed the difference between panic and awe at length in my book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Present_Shock:_When_Everything_Happens_Now"><em>Present Shock</em>.</a> I tried to show how digital technologies “collapse” narrative, and suggested how this could lead vulnerable people toward paranoid and conspiratorial substitutes for linear story. We have seen that sad possibility play out even worse than I feared.</p>

<p>Instead of doubling down on the extractive and distracting technologies that substitute for awe with shots of adrenaline, we must employ styles of education and arts that engender more of an embrace of the moment. Through experiences of awe, we build tolerance for a sustainable present. It may also mean breaking free of the styles of narrative on which we’ve become to dependent: stories with beginnings, middles, and endings. Crisis, climax, and sleep. They train us to see that heightened state of awareness as unsustainable. Worse, they train us to believe that an ending is desirable. The hero is either victorious or vanquished, but at least the story ends and we know who “won.”</p>

<p>Instead, dispensing with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Finite_and_Infinite_Games">finite games for infinite ones</a> and embracing awe as a steady state possibility, we can create theater, film, TV, research and education that promotes the collective dynamic over individual assessment and achievement. We encourage the creation of art and culture that is recalibrating, and technology that is non-abrasive to the nervous system. Stuff that engenders awe.</p>

<p>We stop using technology on people in an effort to program them, and instead provide the tools, sensibilities, socialization, and courage we need to program the world ourselves, together.</p>

<p>That’s the register I’m aiming for. Not a new ledger through which to do our accounting, but a new register in which to sing the human song, together.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the last in a series of five pieces about changing the register, which just means engendering the attitudes and behaviors we want to see in ourselves by intervening in the cultural landscape instead of manipulating people. The first three interventions were to Denaturalize Power, Trigger Agency, and Resocialize People. I saved the best one for last.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_ya7b5ixhmeea2fj8.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_ya7b5ixhmeea2fj8.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Individual Liberty is No Longer the Goal</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/individual-liberty-is-no-longer-the-goal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Individual Liberty is No Longer the Goal" /><published>2023-04-11T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-11T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/individual-liberty-is-no-longer-the-goal</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/individual-liberty-is-no-longer-the-goal.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is the fourth in a series of pieces on instigating social change by focusing less on changing or manipulating people than</em> <a href="https://medium.com/@rushkoff/dont-get-people-to-do-anything-9d59a1cf29a0"><em>changing the “register</em></a><em>.” I got the word “register” from</em> <a href="https://www.teamhuman.fm/episodes/242-marina-gorbis-jerry-davis"><em>business ethicist Jerry Davis</em></a><em>, with whom I’m working on an initiative called Equitable Enterprise at Institute for the Future. He doesn’t mean changing the cash register, or moving to a blockchain ledger. Rather, he means moving from industrial, growth-based values to ones of mutuality and collaborative commerce.</em></p>

<p><em>We have the math and economics to show how a circular economy distributes greater prosperity to more people, more sustainably than extractive competitive one. But shifting from one to the other would require a substantial shift in values. We’re talking about a change of mindset, paradigm, social norms, collective narrative, or “register” from personal profit (and individual survival) to one of mutual prosperity (and collective flourishing).</em></p>

<p><em>This, then got me thinking about any effort at social change, and how we may be able to shift from an industrial age model of initiating change by manipulating people, to a model where we work on changing the environment in order to make new attitudes and approaches easier to adopt. Rather than changing people or “getting people” to do x or y, we create the conditions that engender the attitudes and behaviors more conducive to the kind of society we want to live in.</em></p>

<p><em>And yes, these are actually also the same sorts of conditions we need in order to train our emerging AIs to serve the long-term interests of humans and other life. If AI’s continue to train on our current social norms, they’re only going to exacerbate our penchant for growth and individualism at the expense of everything else. So the four interventions I’m proposing are as much a way of offering them some alternative pathways as it is for us.</em></p>

<p><em>The first two were to</em> <a href="https://medium.com/@rushkoff/if-it-aint-real-don-t-fix-it-c080b27f82c5"><em>denaturalize power</em></a> <em>(which means helping people recognize the underlying assumptions embedded in our world are inventions and social constructions that we mistake for the conditions of nature) and to</em> <a href="https://medium.com/p/94cb071e2950/edit"><em>trigger agency</em></a> <em>(giving people the confidence to remake those social constructions in ways that better serve us).</em></p>

<p>Inorder to do any of this, we must learn to work together and recognize that — contrary to our current social maps — being human is a team sport. The third intervention I’m calling for is to <strong>Re-socialize the People</strong>. This was the message of my <a href="https://wwnorton.com/books/Team-Human/"><em>Team Human</em></a> manifesto. We were taught in school that nature is an entirely competitive affair. Radical libertarians, in particular, like to point out that we are living in a Darwin battle for survival of the fittest individual.</p>

<p>If we actually read Darwin, however, we find that he was not depicting a competitive world at all. Rather, on page after page he was marveling at the ways that species cooperate and collaborate among themselves and each other to ensure mutual survival. As more recent science has revealed, trees in the forest don’t compete with each other for sunlight. The larger tree doesn’t shade and steal light from its smaller counterparts, but shares its energy with them through an underground network of roots and mycellium. Then, when it loses its leaves in the winter, the smaller evergreen trees return energy back to them.</p>

<p>Likewise, under the assumptions of a digital media environment, Marx is understood as a top down systems theorist looking to impose big solutions, at scale, on whole nations or continents. Socialism sounds like a totalizing operating system on the order of capitalism or globalism. But social-ism was actually meant to retrieve the pre-industrial social reality that allowed for the creation and exchange of value between real people. Not everything goes on the ledger. Many of our exchanges are purely social, even if real value like food or services are offered.</p>

<p>Resocializing people simply means making it easier for people to ask each other for favors, to establish rapport, and to build solidarity. Why are so many of us reluctant to borrow a tool from a neighbor instead of buying a new one from the store? Are we afraid to owe them a favor? Are we worried about the tool company having to lay off workers? Is there really no way for us to work less as we share more of what we have in abundance? Once we are socialized, “economics” becomes a last resort — not the default operating system but a fallback mechanism for when the social fabric has torn. It’s for when we lose our ability to work together as “the people,” and devolve back to individualism.</p>

<p>Being human is a team sport. The extent to which we may represent the most evolved species is only a reflection of how well we have learned to communicate and collaborate. While digital technology often undermines these social mechanisms, real world face-to-face contact recalibrates our nervous systems, and establishes the rapport required to achieve solidarity. We cannot denaturalize power or trigger agency, alone.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the fourth in a series of pieces on instigating social change by focusing less on changing or manipulating people than changing the “register.” I got the word “register” from business ethicist Jerry Davis, with whom I’m working on an initiative called Equitable Enterprise at Institute for the Future. He doesn’t mean changing the cash register, or moving to a blockchain ledger. Rather, he means moving from industrial, growth-based values to ones of mutuality and collaborative commerce.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_eyap448ns9i0j4mn.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_eyap448ns9i0j4mn.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wanna Make Something Together?</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/wanna-make-something-together.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wanna Make Something Together?" /><published>2023-04-08T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-08T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/wanna-make-something-together</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/wanna-make-something-together.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been teaching in the Media Studies department at CUNY/Queens College for the past, gosh, eight years. This coming Fall, I’ll become the new director of the graduate program, where we’ve been focused on media studies scholarship in the context of social change and social justice. It’s been fun and enriching, but increasingly people have been asking for something more hands-on, embedded in community, or expressed in the form of performing arts or media activism.</p>

<p>Luckily, the folks at the Drama, Theater and Dance department have been thinking along the same lines, so we’re going to be joining forces to pilot a new <a href="https://www.qc.cuny.edu/academics/ms/media-arts-and-performance/">MA track in Media Arts and Performance</a> beginning in Fall 23. This post is my invitation to join us.</p>

<p>Most basically, this is an MA program for actors, dancers, writers, directors, technicians, set and costume designers, media makers, activists, and performance studies scholars interested in performance and media as a form of social practice, activism, or community building. It is appropriate for those pursuing careers in the performing arts, arts education, media arts, arts activism, or performing arts scholarship.</p>

<p>I’m hoping this is where you’d come for an MA degree if—like me—you aspire to be the next <a href="https://revbilly.com/">Reverend Billy</a>, <a href="https://theyesmen.org/">YesMen</a>, <a href="https://www.ali-ferzat.com/">Ali Ferzat</a>, <a href="https://midianinja.org/">Midianinja</a>, <a href="https://projects.jennyholzer.com/">Jenny Holzer</a>, <a href="https://www.elevator.org/">Elevator Repair Service</a>, <a href="https://www.morbidanatomy.org/">Museum of Morbid Anatomy</a>, <a href="https://www.shamellbell.com/about-shamell">Dr. Sharmell Bell</a>, <a href="https://www.studioamelia.com/about">Amelia Winger-Bearskin</a>, or <a href="https://www.sfmt.org/">San Fransciso Mime Troupe</a>. It’s less for performers who want to headline at Lincoln Center than those who want to discover and promote the untold stories of an under-represented community. Less for a filmmaker who wants to make the next Marvel blockbuster than one who wants to experiment with new narrative structures that don’t reinforce existing hierarchies. Less for someone who wants to use AI to create convincing special effects than someone who wants to reveal the hidden biases of AI through live improvisation or an interactive installation.</p>

<p>The program will specialize in integration of media arts and performance, such as interactive theater, online performance, augmented reality and dance, and performative media. The overall focus of the Media Studies department remains squarely on media studies and social justice, cultural change, racial equality and representation, climate, economic equality, and media activism. So we will be particularly interested in working with artists, performers, and media makers who care about these issues and related ones.</p>

<p>Because we are a boutique program (maybe twenty students) we will be offering courses with broad scope—ones like Media Archeology, Performance Practicum, or Media &amp; Performance—so that you can bring your own work or line of inquiry to the table. A course in media archeology, for example, will let one student explore the archived history of dance in 1930’s China, while someone else studies game emulators of the 1990’s, and someone else researches preserved occult technologies of the Theosophists. The courses are more like containers for doing independent work, together.</p>

<p>Students will also receive credit for supervised projects such as playwriting, theater productions, dance, choreography, public theater, media activism, documentary, augmented theater, community engagement, primary school workshops, internships with media or performing arts organizations, and teaching.</p>

<p>Luckily, because it’s a public university <a href="https://www.cuny.edu/financial-aid/tuition-and-college-costs/tuition-fees/#graduate-tuition">the cost of an MA through CUNY</a> can be an order of magnitude less than one of those private MA puppy mills. Closer to 10k/year than the 40k to 60k it costs elsewhere. But you can also apply as a non-matriculated student and just take individual courses, a la carte.</p>

<p>If you’re not looking for education or a degree but still want to play, feel free to get in touch once we’ve launched in September. We’ll be running a colloquium series for artists, scholars, and media activists to share their work with the community, and creating opportunities for people to workshop ideas with our students.</p>

<p>The sooner you apply (<a href="https://www.qc.cuny.edu/ga/media-studies-master-of-arts/">right here</a>), the better, but applications are accepted up until the “extended deadline” of June 15. Mention in your essay that you’re interested in this new track. Of course, you can use that same link to apply for our regular MA program in Media Studies with an emphasis on social change.</p>

<p>I’m not just writing this as an ad or announcement (though I am hoping to attract some interesting people to this program). Rather, I just spent a week grading a stack of undergraduate papers, almost half of which were written by ChatGPT. It got me thinking long and hard about people who end up in courses of study for the wrong reasons, and even more about creating the kinds of programs where no one would think to delegate their assignments to an AI platform.</p>

<p>Or if they did do that, it would be for fun, subversive reasons. The same sorts of reasons that would inspire the renegades, spoilsports, and interventionists who would think to come and play with us in this new program. We’ll see. Honestly, this hasn’t happened yet, and whatever does happen will depend on who shows up. I’m hoping that includes some of you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been teaching in the Media Studies department at CUNY/Queens College for the past, gosh, eight years. This coming Fall, I’ll become the new director of the graduate program, where we’ve been focused on media studies scholarship in the context of social change and social justice. It’s been fun and enriching, but increasingly people have been asking for something more hands-on, embedded in community, or expressed in the form of performing arts or media activism.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_jctu5_0pu3grjbevs858_q.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_jctu5_0pu3grjbevs858_q.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Everything is Up for Discussion</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/everything-is-up-for-discussion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Everything is Up for Discussion" /><published>2023-03-31T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-31T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/everything-is-up-for-discussion</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/everything-is-up-for-discussion.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This is the second of four “interventions” for changing the register from digital industrialism to something, well, better. The</em> <a href="https://rushkoff.medium.com/dont-get-people-to-do-anything-9d59a1cf29a0"><em>idea of changing the register is introduced here</em></a><em>, and the first intervention,</em> <a href="https://rushkoff.medium.com/if-it-aint-real-don-t-fix-it-c080b27f82c5"><em>“denaturalize power” is here</em></a><em>.</em></p>

<p>The first time I used a word processing program was in the computer lab at college. When I was ready to save my file, the grad student supervising the lab asked me how I wanted to save my file: as a “protected” file that no one else could open, a “read only” file that other people could open, or a “read-write” file that people could not only open but also <em>change</em>. I went with read-write, of course.</p>

<p>I’ll never forget how that concept stayed with me as I left the lab and considered the other media and institutions in my world. Which things were read-only, and which were read-write? And why?</p>

<p>Why is money read-only? Or religion? What if we could change them? How much of the world was arbitrarily protected from our intervention, who got to make those decisions, and what happens if we violate them? I had been raised in the read-only media environment of television, and learned to be a spectator. Might the read-write possibilities of the digital environment grant me greater access to the dashboard of civilization?</p>

<p>For me, that’s what the digital renaissance was all about. And the cultural institutions with which I allied myself at the time — Mondo2000, the Well, Free Software Foundation, the SF Rave scene, the open source community, the cypherpunks, and the cyberpunks—all seemed to be about developing and activating this sensibility. The world is open to our intervention; anything and everything can be reprogrammed, from the norms of gender and the rules of the economy to the articles of the US Constitution. If they’re locked down by laws, chances are it’s because they’re actually changeable. We’ve simply forgotten.</p>

<p>By denaturalizing power (what I wrote about in <a href="https://rushkoff.medium.com/if-it-aint-real-don-t-fix-it-c080b27f82c5">the previous piece</a>), we reveal that the codes we have been living by were actually written by people to favor their own interests. This then triggers our sense of agency to change them. Most of the social and economic laws we accept at face value were written in the era of the printing press or at best, the age of top-down broadcast media. A digital environment offers us new possibilities of access, authorship, and agency. We are free to develop, as I explained in my 2010 book <a href="https://www.orbooks.com/catalog/program/"><em>Program or Be Programmed</em></a>, from player to cheater to author to programmer — and not just online, but in everything.</p>

<p>I’m not calling for a revolution here, but a change in orientation. The laws we accept as sacred inviolable truths are not from God at all, but fungible human artifacts we can adapt or discard. We mustn’t mistake this for the accelerationist anti-institutionalism of those who want to tear down the institutions of democracy altogether. Rather, we reclaim the capacity to revise, rescript, and reprogram them ourselves. We can retrieve the functions that our institutions have failed to deliver, and find new ways to fulfill them.</p>

<p>We are in charge here.</p>

<p><em>Next week, the third intervention: resocializing people.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is the second of four “interventions” for changing the register from digital industrialism to something, well, better. The idea of changing the register is introduced here, and the first intervention, “denaturalize power” is here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_goxgd_9lufb5lzjd.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_goxgd_9lufb5lzjd.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">If it Ain’t Real, Don’t Fix It</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/if-it-ain-t-real-don-t-fix-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="If it Ain’t Real, Don’t Fix It" /><published>2023-03-27T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-27T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/if-it-ain-t-real-don-t-fix-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/if-it-ain-t-real-don-t-fix-it.html"><![CDATA[<p>While giving a recent television interview about promise and peril AI, I was asked about the inevitable “unemployment problem.” What would we do about all the jobs that would be lost to AI? I paused, then almost jokingly responded, “what if it’s not an unemployment problem but the unemployment solution?” It may sound like a jest, but who wants a job, really, anyway? Jobs are actually a rather recent invention, created after the establishment of “chartered monopolies” that made it illegal for any small business to compete with one of the king’s officially chartered companies. Instead of making shoes and selling them at the market, the cobbler now had to work for His Majesty’s Royal Shoe Company — a favored merchant who offered a kickback to the Crown for the exclusive right to monopolize the sector.</p>

<p>In fact, that’s the moment in European history when the clock went on the highest tower in the town, as if to “naturalize” the human invention of wage labor and the power that embedded in the earliest corporations. Until that moment, the only people who sold their time were indentured servants. Five hundred years later, we accept such employment as a condition of nature. This is the history I chronicled in my book <a href="https://rushkoff.com/books/life-inc/">Life Inc</a>, which sought to demonstrate that both central currency and corporations were invented by particular people with particular agendas at a particular moment in history. We need not accept them as fixed features of our world. As the book’s flap copy plainly announces, “This didn’t just happen.”</p>

<p>That’s why the first intervention to <a href="https://rushkoff.medium.com/dont-get-people-to-do-anything-9d59a1cf29a0">change the register</a> that I’m calling for—the one that’s a prerequisite for all the others—is to <strong>denaturalize power</strong>. This simply means helping people recognize the underlying assumptions embedded in our world: inventions and social constructions that we mistakenly accept as conditions of nature. We are misconstruing the maps for the territory, and must work to reveal their origins, manufacture, biases and agendas.</p>

<p>Sure, as activists and change agents, we can argue over how the maps are being drawn. We can argue about who owns which piece of land. But more importantly, we need to remember that the maps themselves are not real. We must not simply compete or cheat, but rather play “spoilsport” to the accepted game, and reveal it as a human construction.</p>

<p>Denaturalizing power means revealing social constructions as inventions of people, not pre-existing conditions of reality. God didn’t invent jobs, rent, prisons, policing, money, maps, cars, school or social networks. These are human institutions, developed at particular moments in history, by people with particular agendas. Some of them may be relevant and beneficial to people today, but all of them are manufactured and open to our reinvention. Just because we are born into a world that has these things doesn’t mean they are sacred or indisputable fixtures.</p>

<p>I recently argued during a talk that people begin sharing big ticket industrial tools like lawnmowers and snowblowers. Why not have one lawnmower per block, I suggested. Someone raised their hand and asked, “that sounds great, but what about the people working at the lawnmower company?” There it is: the preexisting condition. The seemingly unmovable piece.</p>

<p>Are we really here to serve the economy, or is it here to serve us? Do technology businesses really need to grow exponentially and have an “exit” in order to be successful? Why do we each need to save enough money in our working years to support ourselves in retirement? Why do crypto currencies have to support investors betting on the rising value of a token, rather than people who want to transact in a less expensive way? Does crypto have to reify the values of traditional central currency, or can it reveal and challenge them?</p>

<p>In order to begin asking these important kinds of questions, we need to be able to distinguish between what is really here, and what was put here; what we actually need, and what we’re told we want; what are the pre-existing conditions of the natural world, and what are the synthetic rules and value statements we’ve been led to believe are the laws of nature.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[While giving a recent television interview about promise and peril AI, I was asked about the inevitable “unemployment problem.” What would we do about all the jobs that would be lost to AI? I paused, then almost jokingly responded, “what if it’s not an unemployment problem but the unemployment solution?” It may sound like a jest, but who wants a job, really, anyway? Jobs are actually a rather recent invention, created after the establishment of “chartered monopolies” that made it illegal for any small business to compete with one of the king’s officially chartered companies. Instead of making shoes and selling them at the market, the cobbler now had to work for His Majesty’s Royal Shoe Company — a favored merchant who offered a kickback to the Crown for the exclusive right to monopolize the sector.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_6zuw7u_wynzw6w63.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_6zuw7u_wynzw6w63.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t “Get” People to Do Anything</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/don-t-get-people-to-do-anything.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t “Get” People to Do Anything" /><published>2023-03-23T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-23T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/don-t-get-people-to-do-anything</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/don-t-get-people-to-do-anything.html"><![CDATA[<p>Nearly every time I’m on a panel or in a conversation about civic harmony, social change or economic equality, someone eventually asks, “I agree, but how are we going to get people to….?” And that’s when the conversation turns to education, publicity campaigns, memes, or some other well-intentioned form of social engineering. If only we could get people to…</p>

<p>We all hope to steer our society away from the inequality, extraction, externalities, and power imbalances of the industrial economy, but — not surprisingly — our first impulse is to impose the same sorts of top-down, command-and-control solutions typical of the industrial age.</p>

<p>Tech developers and entrepreneurs, in particular, have become aware of the various harms and externalities of the technologies they have built, and want to reverse some of these media effects. As if seeing the light, they now want to create apps and platforms that undo the problems that their original apps and platforms caused. So they create meditation apps to calm minds that have been intentionally made anxious by social media, or wellness platforms to “nudge” people toward healthier uses of their time than doom-scrolling on a new app. There are even whole organizations and institutes dedicated to developing “humane technologies” that treat people more benevolently than their predecessors.</p>

<p>But the orientation of these efforts is all wrong. They’re all about using technology on people, rather than people using technology. “Humane” is the way companies claim to treat cage-free chickens: a commitment by an industry to raise and slaughter its living commodities as painlessly as possible. That’s not good enough. The question should not be about how humanely our technologies program human beings, but about how well human beings can program technology.</p>

<p>This same premise applies to any effort at social change: Are we trying to program people to behave better, or are we creating better conditions for such positive change to take place? If we want to change the cultural and economic climate from extractive digital industrialism to something more human centered, we don’t do this by manipulating or reprogramming people. That only exacerbates the problem. It’s an artifact of the dominating, colonialist mindset of the social programmer.</p>

<p>Whenever we hear people talk of “getting people” to be more generous, more concerned about the climate, more committed to social justice, or even more compliant with health mandates, we must pause and reconsider. Improving our social capacities, encouraging our civic duty, and retrieving our human sensibilities are terrific goals, but we don’t achieve them by attempting to engineer human behavior. Even the crafting and deployment of “memes”, while fun, amounts to <em>operating</em> people rather than providing people with the tools they need to navigate and influence the world.</p>

<p>Using tech or techniques on people is a form of Industrial Age thinking, reducing people and human culture to operating systems. It’s the soulless landscape of auto-tuning and the manufacturing of consent. True cultural change requires transcending this mindset. Instead of “getting people” to do one thing or another, we engender a culture or landscape where new possibilities and alternative approaches are likely to spawn and spread.</p>

<p>I’ve been working for the past year with The Institute for the Future’s <a href="https://www.iftf.org/projects/equitable-enterprise-initiative/">Equitable Enterprise Initiative</a>, seeking solutions for some of the inequalities inherent to corporate capitalism. We have, likewise, concluded that we need to change what we’ve started to call the “register” or attitudinal environment, or underlying assumptions steering our business and economic choices. The current register of competition and accumulation encourages businesses to grow at any cost, investors to seek “exits,” and individuals to orient their careers toward self-sufficiency and personal retirement. With a register like that, how do we “get” people to engage in alternative behaviors, like sharing, mutual aid, or cooperative enterprises? We don’t.</p>

<p>Rather than changing the people, we change the register.</p>

<p>Fortuitously, over the course of my career I’ve identified four “interventions” on which I have relied on (or even based whole books) to open people to new possibilities. I’ll list them here, and follow up with a piece on how each one works over the coming weeks.</p>

<p><strong>Denaturalize Power.</strong> Help people recognize the underlying assumptions embedded in our world are inventions and social constructions that we mistake for the conditions of nature.</p>

<p><strong>Trigger Agency.</strong> By denaturalizing power, we reveal that the codes we live by were written by people at particular moments in history, with particular agendas in mind. This then triggers our sense of agency about rewriting such codes ourselves, in ways that benefit more people and reflect our own values.</p>

<p><strong>ReSocialize People.</strong> In order to do any of this, we must learn to work together and recognize that — contrary to our current social maps — being human is a team sport.</p>

<p><strong>Cultivate Awe.</strong> Awe means experiencing oneself as part of something greater. In the current register, this is associated with a diminishment of personal freedom, when it is actually the fuller realization of individual and collective identities as mutually reinforcing.</p>

<p>I’ll be sharing more about Denaturalizing Power next week. I’ll also be inviting some of the folks working on Equitable Enterprise Initiative to come on my Team Human podcast to talk about changing the register.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nearly every time I’m on a panel or in a conversation about civic harmony, social change or economic equality, someone eventually asks, “I agree, but how are we going to get people to….?” And that’s when the conversation turns to education, publicity campaigns, memes, or some other well-intentioned form of social engineering. If only we could get people to…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_b5heolrv8fjakpqu.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_b5heolrv8fjakpqu.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Day the Dotcom Bust Began</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/the-day-the-dotcom-bust-began.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Day the Dotcom Bust Began" /><published>2023-03-08T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-08T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/the-day-the-dotcom-bust-began</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/the-day-the-dotcom-bust-began.html"><![CDATA[<p>The Internet changed for me on the morning of January 10, 2000, when an editor from the <em>New York Times</em> called to ask if I could bang out an OpEd by that afternoon. I was thrilled. The culture of the net, which I had been writing about since the late 1980’s, was finally mainstream enough for the Gray Lady to solicit a think piece from a fringe, cyberpunk writer like me.</p>

<p>But the editor wanted my commentary on something slightly different: Time Warner, a venerable “old media” company, had just announced it would be acquired by America Online — an internet access company that had only been in existence for a decade. Did this mean the Internet had truly arrived? Could I please explain what this merger really meant, in plain English?</p>

<p>I didn’t want to give up the opportunity, but this wasn’t really my beat. I was a media and culture writer. I knew about movies, television, computer games, online communities, and the subcultures they spawn. I was interested in virtual reality, electronic dance parties, chaos math, digital storytelling, media viruses and fractals.</p>

<p>This was a business story. What did I know about stock-only deals, board representation, and market caps? I figured I’d wing it. The <em>Times’</em> editor saw this deal as the “birth of the digital economy,” and if it was, I wanted to be present and weigh in.</p>

<p>So I analyzed the merger from my own perspective, that of a media theorist and financial naif. A venerable conglomerate with real assets including a film library, magazine empire, theme parks, movie studios, and thousands of miles of television cable was about to merge with the guys who mailed pink-wrapped “10 Hours Free Access” CDs to pretty much every home in America. According to the terms of the deal, the two companies would combine into one, with AOL shareholders owning 55%, and TimeWarner just 45% of the new company’s stock.</p>

<p>How could America Online, a company with virtually no real assets, accomplish such a feat? Yes, AOL had accumulated a few million users, but I had been hearing that the new subscriber rate was slowing, not gaining, for a few months by then. The only thing peaking about AOL at the turn of the century was its stock price.</p>

<p>Then, all of a sudden, the move made sense to the video game geek within me: AOL was spending its “in-world” fantasy money. Of course. AOL founder Steve Case was cashing in his chips, exchanging his speculative dot com paper for a majority stake in a real company with real assets. Moreover, if he was choosing to do it now, it meant he believed that his AOL stock had hit its peak. To me, AOL’s purchase of TimeWarner suggested that the irrational exuberance surrounding technology stocks had climaxed: the dot com boom was ending.</p>

<p>So I wrote all this down and sent it to the editor by the 3pm deadline. An hour later, the phone rang. “We can’t run this!” he said. “Everybody is saying the deal is a great thing, and you’re trying to argue that it’s going to <em>fail</em>? That it’s some kind of bait and switch?”</p>

<p>“Yeah, TimeWarner is getting screwed,” I replied. “But AOL may be over, too. This is beginning of the end of the dotcom boom.”</p>

<p>“Well, we can’t run a negative piece about a merger that everyone in the Business Section says is unequivocally great for old and new media alike.”</p>

<p>“Maybe you should have someone from Business write it, then.”</p>

<p>They did. Along with hundreds of other editorials from business experts, the <em>New York Times</em> OpEd page extolled the virtues of the deal. I got my own piece placed in <em>The Guardian of London</em>, where contrarian views about American business were more welcome. But the overwhelming consensus was that we were witnessing a tide change in business history: the young eating the mature, new media conquering old media, creative destruction, the dawn of the digital economy, or the Internet Revolution.</p>

<p>From my perspective — that of a media theorist — this wasn’t a revolutionary moment at all but a highly <em>reactionary</em> one. It’s not just that the story of the Internet itself had moved from the culture section of the newspaper to the business pages. It’s that we were beginning to care less about how this technology could augment humanity, and more about how it could bolster a flagging stock exchange. The excitement around digital culture, the sexiness of people engaging with one another through media or making new software for free instead of simply watching television all night, was serving as little more than the hype for a big deal on the old economy’s stock exchange. It was no longer about changing the world, but keeping the old system firmly in place. Digital innovations were simply new ways to maintain the status quo.</p>

<p>Besides, two months later, the dot com bubble did burst, the NASDAQ crashed, and the very same newspapers that had celebrated the AOL-TimeWarner merger were now decrying it as an epic failure on the part of TimeWarner’s CEO, a former director of the New York Stock Exchange no less, Gerald Levin. People blamed his poor judgment on the trauma of losing his son, and watched, stunned, as $200 billion of shareholder money seemingly evaporated. The Internet Revolution was derided as a Ponzi scheme.</p>

<p>Moreover, the marriage of old and new media did not infuse TimeWarner with the disruptive values of Internet culture. The resulting company didn’t become more adventurous or innovative. Quite to the contrary, it became much more traditionally corporate in spirit, obsessed with the bottom line. They fired CNN’s Ted Turner — the 1980s cable television renegade was simply too radical and spontaneous for this supposedly 21st Century “new media” company. Magazine editors, who had previously focused on finding outlier writers and stories were told to develop shorter, more web and ad-friendly copy. The promised “synergies” between print and digital media amounted to diluting what was left of revered properties such as <em>Time</em> and <em>Sports Illustrated</em> with cheap online “extensions”. They recycled copy in the hope of selling a few banner ads, but ended up mostly giving away online space as a perk to those who advertised in the print publications.</p>

<p>Worse, the new combined company had to justify a tremendous valuation, or market capitalization, to its shareholders. The market cap of a company is its total worth — in stock. It’s the price of a single share multiplied by the number shares out there. Normally, it has some relationship to the amount of money a company makes. But with new and seemingly infinite business sector like the early Internet, it can be based on wildly speculative guesses about future growth. To those who didn’t know a lot about the way the Internet works, AOL seemed to have a lock on “dial-up,” which was the way most people connected to the Web. So — in a practice that’s still used in business plans today — they multiplied the number of people in the world by the cost of monthly access, and figured that was AOL’s true value.</p>

<p>But now that AOL’s Internet subscriber rate had plateaued, the old media side of the new AOL-TimeWarner was going to have to make up the difference. Somehow. That would be tricky for a traditional publishing company in an era of digital disruption. So instead of finding new revenue sources (known as growing the top line), the company implemented a tried and true method of pleasing shareholders: cutting expenses. TimeWarner offered its staffs “packages” to resign, slashed research budgets, and even carted out the water coolers. The company sold off productive assets such as Six Flags theme parks and even their cable company, Roadrunner. In order to survive, TimeWarner eventually had to spin off AOL entirely, leaving TimeWarner back where it was — except without its assets, personnel, cash, or stock value.</p>

<p>So, at least in this case, creative destruction resulted in something more like destructive destruction. The new industry didn’t replace the old one with something better; it just destroyed everything in the path of its exit strategy. It turns out Steve Case’s team had been looking for months for a way to spend his high-priced shares while there was still time. Instead of investing in digital innovation, he hired investment bank Salomon Smith Barney to find an acquisition target. This was not any sort of new media strategy. It was plain old, buy-low-sell-high horse trading, amplified by the massive bubble of digital finance. As Ted Turner now explains it in characteristic hyperbole, “the Time Warner-AOL merger should pass into history like the Vietnam War and the Iraq and Afghanistan wars. It’s one of the biggest disasters that have occurred to our country.” And at the time they thought <em>I</em> was being pessimistic.</p>

<p>In retrospect, the problems underlying the merger look obvious — even to traditional economists and business strategists. Yet even today the vast majority of professional observers seem incapable of recognizing how these same dynamics are still at play in the business landscape. This is because the experts tend to accept the business landscape as a pre-existing condition of nature. It is not. The rules of our economy were invented by human beings, at particular moments in history, with particular goals and agendas. It’s like a computer program, with accumulated lines of code written by developers throughout history with specific functions in mind. By refusing to acknowledge this, we end up incapable of getting beneath the surface. We end up transacting, and living, at the mercy of a system — of a medium, really.</p>

<p>To a media theorist, anyway, the real power underlying our emerging digital environment has less to do with digital technologies or computer algorithms than it does with the hands-on approach such an environment engenders. Members of a digital society are implicitly invited to program and reprogram the various operating systems that shape our world. Everything is up for grabs. All it takes is a willingness to see seemingly given circumstances as up for discussion.</p>

<p>By the same token, in a digital age, the refusal to have those discussions — to consider who or what we’re programming for — can be perilous. Instead of reevaluating the economic status quo, we simply amp it up with powerful, blazingly fast, and ultimately unpredictable technologies. Instead of recognizing, adapting or transcending the underlying game, we use software to game the system — like pro athletes using steroids to boost performance. Then we wonder why there’s so much collateral damage to the humans our economy was supposedly built to serve.</p>

<p>We have yet to learn the lesson of the dotcom boom and bust. We are bound to repeat it until we do.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Internet changed for me on the morning of January 10, 2000, when an editor from the New York Times called to ask if I could bang out an OpEd by that afternoon. I was thrilled. The culture of the net, which I had been writing about since the late 1980’s, was finally mainstream enough for the Gray Lady to solicit a think piece from a fringe, cyberpunk writer like me.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_ssmagisxywgndnqlqnv9vg.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_ssmagisxywgndnqlqnv9vg.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t Forget the Covid Miracles</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/don-t-forget-the-covid-miracles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don’t Forget the Covid Miracles" /><published>2023-03-04T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-04T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/don-t-forget-the-covid-miracles</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/don-t-forget-the-covid-miracles.html"><![CDATA[<p>Three years in, it’s not too early to begin reflecting on what Covid taught us about ourselves and our communities.</p>

<p>Sure, lots of people—the wealthy, in particular—retreated to their vacation homes, outfitted them with new WiFi, purchased special high-priority accounts with their favorite gig-worker delivery services, and subscribed to the best TV and hi-def audio channels that Hollywood and Silicon Valley have to offer. Between craft beers, Microsoft Teams, and Grogu, life was good. During this interregnum between Covid and the next disaster, I’m sure these folks are busy constructing the rec rooms, pools, security systems, and hydroponic gardens their facilities lacked on the first go round.</p>

<p>But the rest of us, or at least a bunch of the rest of us, learned something very different: the power of mutual aid.</p>

<p>In spite of the ridicule they received (sometimes from people like me), parents of all economic classes formed “bubbles” with neighbors for their Zoom-schooled kids to do homework together, or to home school their children collectively. People brought food to neighbors, and checked in the elderly. “I’m sorry I can’t open the door to thank you,” one neighbor would shout through the storm door whenever I brought her groceries. As if she should be thanking me, when I am the one getting the joy of doing something positive in dark times.</p>

<p>In less affluent areas, many smaller <a href="https://citylimits.org/2021/09/24/a-year-and-a-half-into-pandemic-nycs-mutual-aid-movement-at-a-turning-point/">grocery stores teamed up with mutual aid societies</a> to post lists of the specific food items that people needed, so that donor customers could purchase them. The charity food pantry in my neighborhood became so flush with food during the pandemic that organizers began distributing to those in neighboring towns.</p>

<p>Businesses found ways to shorten shifts and reduce work weeks in order to keep employees on the payroll (and with health insurance) until things picked up again. <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0973005221991624">Cooperatives fared better </a>than most other businesses, however, because their workers and/or customers are their only owners. They are set up to prioritize the interests of their members, not their distant shareholders.</p>

<p>The resilience of cooperatives, networks, non-profits, and other sustainable enterprises challenged the grow-at-any-costs priorities of traditional corporate capitalism, and suggested that aiming for distributed prosperity may be a better long-term strategy than scorched earth extraction.</p>

<p>Now that we are (hopefully) emerging from the Covid crisis, do we really want to return to business as usual? Can we remember witnessing the vulnerability of our convoluted and easily disrupted supply chains? Can we still recognize the hazardous and stressful conditions imposed on frontline workers? Do we still see how the monopolies and monopsomies of the digital and global economy enrich extremely few at the expense of everybody else, as well as the civic sector and the planet?</p>

<p>It’s not about banging pots and pans in the evening to celebrate our frontline workers (though that was certainly a nice gesture); it’s about transitioning to a circular economy characterized by the knowledge that mutuality is more than good business.</p>

<p>It’s contagious.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Three years in, it’s not too early to begin reflecting on what Covid taught us about ourselves and our communities.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_nez9xqqmtmk9fbu8oop91a.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_nez9xqqmtmk9fbu8oop91a.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Having Enough Faith to Question</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/having-enough-faith-to-question.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Having Enough Faith to Question" /><published>2023-02-27T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-27T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/having-enough-faith-to-question</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/having-enough-faith-to-question.html"><![CDATA[<p>Back around the turn of the century, I wrote an article for Adbusters called “The Sabbath Revolt.” I was arguing for a “one-seventh rule” where we reserve one day a week for non-commodified activities. This idea of a day off each week was one of the first things the Israelite slaves gave themselves after escaping from Egypt. And seemed to me it could serve as a safeguard for the coming digital onslaught. If the algorithms and AIs were really going to program us into a new sort of slavery, perhaps withholding 1/7th of our time from them could give us enough pause to reflect and reset on our inherent worth.</p>

<p>The article got me a lot of attention, particularly from Jewish organizations dedicated to keeping the religion going. They were all concerned about declining membership in synagogues and Jewish day schools, and thought someone like me could help them bring Judaism into the era of MTV and the World Wide Web. “Digital Shabbat” might catch on, they suggested.</p>

<p>In speaking with them, though, I realized that most of them didn’t really understand what Judaism was all about. They had mistaken it for a religion — for a set of things to believe in. At least as I understood it, Judaism was originally meant as the way to get <em>over</em> religion. It was a set of practices developed by people who had just suffered through the death cults of the pharaohs. Their mythical patriarch Abraham smashes the idols and instead worships a more abstract, universal God, who slowly recedes and eventually disappears — leaving human beings alone to take care of one another and all living things.</p>

<p>For me, the spirit of the whole enterprise was captured in the image of the very first ark that the Israelites build in the desert (the one that shows up in <em>Indiana Jones</em>). It was just like the ones they had built as slaves in Egypt, except—unlike all of those—there was no statue of a god on the top. Instead, there was an empty space, protected by two cherubs facing one another. The idea was that God shows up in that empty space between two people, really engaging face to face. The “nothing” between us is truly sacred.</p>

<p>So I wrote a book called <em>Nothing Sacred</em>, looking at how this essential insight was surrendered to the practicalities of maintaining a peoplehood, particularly in a world where you’ve been exiled from your homeland and need to get along as a perpetual immigrant. Interestingly, the book got me banned by a few of the Jewish philanthropies who depend on fear of intermarriage, assimilation, or threats to Israel for donations.</p>

<p>What worried them most, however, was that if people started looking at the Torah as an open source proposition up for interpretation, then its role as a land deed would be undermined. If you want to use the Torah as proof of title on Israeli real estate, then you can’t also leave its meaning up to the interpretation of each generation who engages with it. But by denying this exploration, you prevent Judaism from renewing itself.</p>

<p>They accused me of threatening Jewish continuity, but I saw <em>them</em> as a threat to the greater Jewish project — the real continuity of discussion, intepretation, and re-invention. That’s what keeps any tradition alive: continual change, and perpetual refinement. Nothing is too sacred to be questioned and reflected upon. Judaism is powerful enough to stand up to such scrutiny, playfulness, and inquiry. If only those responsible for its institutions had enough faith to let this anti-dogmatic tradition do its thing, it would attract thinkers and seekers, social justice advocates, and intellectuals alike.</p>

<p>As I see it, Judaism is an invitation to participate in a multi-generational project of negotiating nothing short of a just civilization. It’s the original open source tradition, where a simple demonstration of literacy — the b’nai mitzvah—earns one a place at the table. Then, like any posse of hackers, we argue over the code for the rest of our lives.</p>

<p>How well Judaism retrieves these core insights may be less important than whether other institutions are able to do so. Constitutional democratic government, in particular, requires an ongoing, robust discussion of its purpose and function. But to do that, we have to achieve basic literacy in civics. Just like a Jewish kid studies Torah and learns to read Hebrew, would-be participants in democracy must study civics and learn the classical and Enlightenment philosophies that brought us democracy—especially if they mean to challenge them.</p>

<p>We don’t read in order to submit. We read in order to be fit to write, ourselves.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back around the turn of the century, I wrote an article for Adbusters called “The Sabbath Revolt.” I was arguing for a “one-seventh rule” where we reserve one day a week for non-commodified activities. This idea of a day off each week was one of the first things the Israelite slaves gave themselves after escaping from Egypt. And seemed to me it could serve as a safeguard for the coming digital onslaught. If the algorithms and AIs were really going to program us into a new sort of slavery, perhaps withholding 1/7th of our time from them could give us enough pause to reflect and reset on our inherent worth.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_idbjz5m7vluub3vs.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/0_idbjz5m7vluub3vs.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How We Taught Technology to Program Humans</title><link href="/rushkoff-archive/articles/how-we-taught-technology-to-program-humans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How We Taught Technology to Program Humans" /><published>2023-02-17T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-17T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/rushkoff-archive/articles/how-we-taught-technology-to-program-humans</id><content type="html" xml:base="/rushkoff-archive/articles/how-we-taught-technology-to-program-humans.html"><![CDATA[<p>Someday in the not-so-distant future, we may look back on the web and social media, for all their problems, as the benevolent precursors to the thinking machines that took their place. While I’m intrigued as anyone by the way AI chatbots appear to attain sentience, express their desires for human connection, or go entirely off the rails, I am more concerned about our human willingness to accept AI sentience at face value.</p>

<p>In essence, these intriguing demonstrations of apparent AI self-awareness may say less about machine consciousness than they do about their capacity to manipulate human perception. In other words, if AIs are now passing the Turing test, it may say less about how human they have become than how robotic and programmable we have become, ourselves.</p>

<p>With the advantage of zillions of terabytes of data accumulated through years of online self-reporting by humans, AIs know pretty much everything about us. They’ve also been programmed with everything the compliance industry knows about behavioral psychology, human perception, and entrainment. If AIs are instructed to do whatever they can to make us feel attraction, pity, sorrow, guilt, or desire, they will carry out those commands with everything in their arsenal.</p>

<p>It’s not their job to become alive, but to create the <em>illusion</em> that they are alive — all in order to program us humans to do whatever the people, companies, governments, or machines programming them to program us want us to do.</p>

<p>At least to them, that’s what this last thirty years of networks and social media has been about. The consumer-friendly Internet and video games we’ve known so far could be likened to the Catholic missions of the Spanish Empire to the Americas in the 16th century. The missionaries not only converted large portions of the indigenous populations, but conducted what could only be understood today as anthropological research on behalf of the Empire. This both softened the population for the Conquistadors who followed, and gave the invaders the intelligence they needed to subjugate and colonize them.</p>

<p>If Facebook, Amazon, and Google can be thought of as the missionaries who sold us on digital living while collecting our data, then FacebookAI, OpenAI, and DeepMind are the conquistadors coming in for colonization. And no, if we believe what we hear from their own mouths about their intentions, the people building these platforms do not have our best interests at heart. As I documented in <a href="https://wwnorton.com/books/survival-of-the-richest">Survival of the Richest</a>, they are anti-human technosolutionists, survivalists, technomonarchs, and effective altruists, who see humanity as the disposable larval stage of a post-human cyborg empire that will span the heavens.</p>

<p>The answer is not to reject AI, but to work on retrieving and recognizing our humanity so we’re not so easily fooled into submission by these would-be conquerors. That means studying and engaging in community, the arts, spirituality, and play. More of us need to be building and using AI’s that are designed for assisting and augmenting such human choice and activity, rather than controlling it. There may be less money to be made in the short-term, but more of a human civilization to be manifest in the long run.</p>

<p>Maybe instead of being afraid of AI, we should learn to be less afraid of other people. Then we can learn to program our AIs instead of programming one another.</p>]]></content><author><name>Douglas Rushkoff</name></author><category term="_categories/journalism.md" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Someday in the not-so-distant future, we may look back on the web and social media, for all their problems, as the benevolent precursors to the thinking machines that took their place. While I’m intrigued as anyone by the way AI chatbots appear to attain sentience, express their desires for human connection, or go entirely off the rails, I am more concerned about our human willingness to accept AI sentience at face value.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_onpoavm3lkocmk9dbxgrvq.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="/rushkoff-archive/uploads/1_onpoavm3lkocmk9dbxgrvq.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>